

Norwegian Institute for Nature Research

🛘 ~ | 🌌 Matthew.Grainger@nina.no | 🏶 uncertainecologist.netlify.com | 🖸 DrMattG | 💆 Ed\_pheasant

Wildlife, Uncertainty, Evidence synthesis, Decision models

## About me

I am an ecologist, with research interests in how we use knowledge to better inform decision making in species conservation (i.e. "Evidence-based decision making"). I develop opensource tools (in R and Shiny) that help people gather information robustly in a transparent way, interact with that information and make inference from it.

I am currently working on several projects that are fundamentally about how we make open research approaches (i.e. sharing data, sharing code, sharing best practice) as an integrated part of the workflow for biodiversity researchers and how we can take this open research and use it to help decision-makers find optimal solutions.

# **Education and qualifications**

**Newcastle University** 

UK

BSc (Hons) in Zoology

1994 - 1997

**University of Pretoria** 

South Africa

MSc in Conservation & Planning **University of Pretoria** 

2004 - 2005 South Africa

2008 - 2012

PHD ZOOLOGY

# **Employment history**

2021-	Researcher, NINA, Trondheim, Norway
2019-2021	Postdoctoral Fellow, NINA, Trondheim, Norway
2014-2019	Postdoctoral Research Associate, Newcastle University, UK
2013-2014	Postdoctoral Research Associate-Research Impact, Newcastle University, UK
2011-2012	Conservation Research and Support Officer, World Pheasant Ass., Newcastle, UK
2005-2006	Research Co-ordinator, Frontier-Tanzania, Tanzania

# Rpackages\_

- 1. Haddaway, N., Grainger, M., & Gray, C. (2021). Citationchaser: Perform forward and backwards chasing in evidence syntheses.
- 2. Haddaway, N., Feierman, A., Grainger, M., Gray, C., Tanriver-Ayder, E., Dhaubanjar, S., & Westgate, M. (2019). Visualisation and mapping for datasets from systematic reviews and maps.
- 3. Gray, C., Grainger, M., & Haddaway, N. (2021). Sysrevdata: Methods for designing multifunctional, machine readable systematic review and map databases.

## **Publications**

#### NR Haddaway, CT Gray, M Grainger

Environmental Evidence

NOVEL TOOLS AND METHODS FOR DESIGNING AND WRANGLING MULTIFUNCTIONAL, MACHINE-READABLE EVIDENCE SYNTHESIS DATABASES

2021

#### G Gupta, M Grainger, JC Dunn, R Sanderson, PJK McGowan

bioRxiv

WHAT IS THE EVIDENCE AVAILABLE TO SUPPORT OUR KNOWLEDGE ABOUT THREATS TO THE CONSERVATION OF GALLIFORMES IN THE GREATER HIMALAYA?

2021

H Downey, T Amano, M Cadotte, CN Cook, SJ Cooke, NR Haddaway, ...

Ecological Solutions and Evidence

TRAINING FUTURE GENERATIONS TO DELIVER EVIDENCE-BASED CONSERVATION AND ECOSYSTEM MANAGEMENT

2021

EVIDENCE SYNTHESIS FOR TACKLING RESEARCH WASTE B Cretois, JDC Linnell, M Grainger, EB Nilsen, JK Rød Global Ecology and Conservation HUNTERS AS CITIZEN SCIENTISTS: CONTRIBUTIONS TO BIODIVERSITY MONITORING IN EUROPE 2020 L Aramyan, M Grainger, K Logatcheva, S Piras, M Setti, G Stewart, ... Measuring Business Excellence FOOD WASTE REDUCTION IN SUPPLY CHAINS THROUGH INNOVATIONS: A REVIEW 2020 W Phumanee, R Steinmetz, R Phoonjampa, T Bejraburnin, M Grainger, ... Ecosphere OCCUPANCY-BASED MONITORING OF UNGULATE PREY SPECIES IN THAILAND INDICATES POPULATION STABILITY, BUT LIMITED RECOVERY TNE Gray, MJ Grainger, R Grosu Conservation Science and Practice CONSERVATION DECISION-MAKING UNDER UNCERTAINTY: IDENTIFYING WHEN TO REINTRODUCE TIGER PANTHERA TIGRIS TO 2020 C Kandemir, C Reynolds, M Verma, M Grainger, G Stewart, S Righi, ... Routledge Handbook of Food Waste DISCRETE EVENT SIMULATION; MACHINE LEARNING; BAYESIAN NETWORKS; AGENT-BASED MODELLING; AND MASS BALANCE **ESTIMATION** M Crane, I Silva, MJ Grainger, GA Gale hioRxiv ON A WING AND A PRAYER: LIMITATIONS AND GAPS IN GLOBAL BAT WING MORPHOLOGY TRAIT DATA FC Bolam, MJ Grainger, KL Mengersen, GB Stewart, WJ Sutherland, ... Biological Reviews USING THE VALUE OF INFORMATION TO IMPROVE CONSERVATION DECISION MAKING 2019 J Carrick, MSAB Abdul Rahim, C Adjei, HHH Ashraa Kalee, SJ Banks, ... Journal of Flood Risk Management IS PLANTING TREES THE SOLUTION TO REDUCING FLOOD RISKS? NR Haddaway, A Feierman, MJ Grainger, CT Gray, E Tanriver-Ayder, ... Environmental evidence EVIÁTLAS: A TOOL FOR VISUALISING EVIDENCE SYNTHESIS DATABASES 2019 B Freeman, D Jiménez-García, B Barca, M Grainger Avian Research USING REMOTELY SENSED AND CLIMATE DATA TO PREDICT THE CURRENT AND POTENTIAL FUTURE GEOGRAPHIC DISTRIBUTION 2019 OF A BIRD AT MULTIPLE SCALES: THE CASE OF AGELASTES MELEAGRIDES. A ... MJ Whittingham, AJ McKenzie, RM Francksen, D Feige, T Cadwallender, ... Bird Study OFFSHORE REFUGES SUPPORT HIGHER DENSITIES AND SHOW SLOWER POPULATION DECLINES OF WINTERING RUDDY 2019 TURNSTONES ARENARIA INTERPRES M Grainger, S Piras, S Righi, M Setti, G Stewart, M Vittuari Refresh INTEGRATED MODEL OF CONSUMER BEHAVIOURS IN RELATION TO FOOD WASTE: BEHAVIOURAL ECONOMICS: D4. 4 LINKING 2019 BAYESIAN AND AGENT-BASED MODELS TO ASSESS CONSUMER FOOD WASTE M Grainger, EB Nilsen NEED FOR TRANSPARENT AND REPEATABLE CONSERVATION FRAMEWORKS: REPLY TO CHILD ET AL. 2019 2019 N SUKUMAL, MJ GRAINGER, T SAVINI Bird Conservation International LOWER LEVELS OF HUMAN DISTURBANCE CORRESPOND WITH LONGER-TERM PERSISTENCE OF ENDANGERED GREEN PEAFOWL 2019 PAVO MUTICUS POPULATIONS PJK McGowan, GB Stewart, G Long, MJ Grainger Nature Sustainability AN IMPERFECT VISION OF INDIVISIBILITY IN THE SUSTAINABLE DEVELOPMENT GOALS 2018 MJ Grainger, L Aramyan, S Piras, TE Quested, S Righi, M Setti, M Vittuari, ... PloS one MODEL SELECTION AND AVERAGING IN THE ASSESSMENT OF THE DRIVERS OF HOUSEHOLD FOOD WASTE TO REDUCE THE 2018 PROBABILITY OF FALSE POSITIVES H Kendall, G Kaptan, G Stewart, M Grainger, S Kuznesof, P Naughton, ... Food Control DRIVERS OF EXISTING AND EMERGING FOOD SAFETY RISKS: EXPERT OPINION REGARDING MULTIPLE IMPACTS 2018 MJ Grainger, L Aramyan, K Logatcheva, S Piras, S Righi, M Setti, ... Global food security THE USE OF SYSTEMS MODELS TO IDENTIFY FOOD WASTE DRIVERS MJ Grainger, PJ Garson, SJ Browne, PJK McGowan, T Savini Biological conservation CONSERVATION STATUS OF PHASIANIDAE IN SOUTHEAST ASIA F Stephenson, AC Mill, CL Scott, GB Stewart, MJ Grainger, NVC Polunin, ... Marine Policy SOCIO-ECONOMIC, TECHNOLOGICAL AND ENVIRONMENTAL DRIVERS OF SPATIO-TEMPORAL CHANGES IN FISHING PRESSURE 2018 S Thunhikorn, MJ Grainger, PJK McGowan, T Savini Avian Research SPATIAL DISTRIBUTION OF DISPLAY SITES OF GREY PEACOCK-PHEASANT IN RELATION TO MICRO-HABITAT AND PREDATORS 2018 DURING THE BREEDING SEASON M Grainger, D Ngoprasert, P McGowan, T Savini Oryx INFORMING DECISIONS ON AN EXTREMELY DATA POOR SPECIES FACING IMMINENT EXTINCTION 2017 Resources, Conservation and **MJ Grainger, GB Stewart** Recycling 2017 THE JURY IS STILL OUT ON SOCIAL MEDIA AS A TOOL FOR REDUCING FOOD WASTE A RESPONSE TO YOUNG ET AL. (2017)

MJ Grainger, FC Bolam, GB Stewart, EB Nilsen

Nature ecology & evolution

2020

LH Aramyan, MJ Grainger, K Logatcheva, S Piras, S Righi, M Setti, ... The FOOD WASTE REDUCTION IN SUPPLY CHAINS THROUGH INNOVATIONS: WHAT FACTORS AFFECT THE DECISION TO ADOPT 2017 INNOVATIONS M Grainger, G Stewart, S Piras, S Righi, M Setti, M Vittuari, LH Aramyan **RFFRFSH** D4. 3-MODEL INTEGRATION: INTEGRATED SOCIO-ECONOMIC MODEL ON FOOD WASTE 2017 M Grainger, G Stewart, S Piras, S Righi, M Setti, M Vittuari, LH Aramyan REFRESH D4. 2-MODEL DEVELOPMENT AND DATA PROTOCOL 2016 RAFFLES BULLETIN OF ZOOLOGY S Thunhikorn, MJ Grainger, PJK McGowan, T Savini ASSESSING THE POPULATION OF GREY PEACOCK-PHEASANT (POLYPLECTRON BICALCARATUM) IN A SOUTHEAST ASIAN 2016 CONSERVATION LANDSCAPE S Thunhikorn, MJ Grainger, PJK McGowan, T Savini **Forktail** METHODS USED TO SURVEY AVIAN SPECIES AND THEIR POTENTIAL FOR SURVEYING GROUND-DWELLING BIRDS IN ASIA 2016 S Thunhikorn, M Grainger, P McGowan Newcastle University A REVIEW OF METHODS USED TO SURVEY AVIAN SPECIES AND THEIR POTENTIAL FOR SURVEYING GROUND-DWELLING BIRDS IN 2016 ASIA Raffles Bulletin of Zoology S Thunhikorn, MJ Grainger, PJK McGowan, T Savini ASSESSING THE POPULATION STATUS OF GREY PEACOCK-PHEASANT (POLYPLECTRON BICALCARATUM) IN HUAI KHA KHAENG, A KEY CONSERVATION LANDSCAPE IN SOUTHEAST ASIA Occasional paper of the IUCN DP Mallon, M Hoffmann, MJ Grainger, F Hibert, N Van Vliet, ... species survival commission AN IUCN SITUATION ANALYSIS OF TERRESTRIAL AND FRESHWATER FAUNA IN WEST AND CENTRAL AFRICA FHA Aalen, MJ Grainger, F Hibert, M Hoffmann, DP Mallon, ... **IUCN** ANALYSE DE SITUATION DE L'UICN CONCERNANT LA FAUNE TERRESTRE ET D'EAU DOUCE EN AFRIQUE CENTRALE ET DE L'OUEST 2015 M Grainger, R van Aarde Ecological Restoration CAN NON-NATIVE SPECIES EXPLAIN PATTERNS OF CONVERGENCE AND DEVIATION IN REGENERATING COASTAL DUNE FOREST? 2015 African Journal of Ecology **MJ Grainger, RJ Van Aarde** THE ROLE OF CANOPY GAPS IN THE REGENERATION OF COASTAL DUNE FOREST M Grainger, P McGowan, A McKenzie, J Minderman, JP Rodriguez, ... METHOD FOR THE ASSESSMENT OF PRIORITIES FOR INTERNATIONAL SPECIES CONSERVATION (MAPISCO) **MJ Grainger, RJ Van Aarde Ecological Restoration** IS SUCCESSION-BASED MANAGEMENT OF COASTAL DUNE FOREST RESTORATION VALID? 2012 Animal Biodiversity and PJK McGowan, LL Owens, MJ Grainger Conservation GALLIFORMES SCIENCE AND SPECIES EXTINCTIONS: WHAT WE KNOW AND WHAT WE NEED TO KNOW 2012 RAR Guldemond, MJ Grainger, MJ Trimble Restoration Ecology WHERE IS THE EVIDENCE FOR ASSESSING EVIDENCE-BASED RESTORATION? COMMENTS ON NTSHOTSHO ET AL.(2010) 2012 MJ Grainger, RJ van Aarde, TD Wassenaar Restoration Ecology LANDSCAPE COMPOSITION INFLUENCES THE RESTORATION OF SUBTROPICAL COASTAL DUNE FOREST **MJ Grainger** University of Pretoria An evaluation of coastal dune forest restoration in Northern KwaZulu-Natal, South Africa 2011 **MJ Grainger, RJ Van Aarde** Wiley-Blackwell RESILIENCE OF THE MEDICINAL PLANT COMMUNITY OF REHABILITATING COASTAL DUNE FORESTS, KWAZULU-NATAL, SOUTH C Bonnington, M Grainger, S Dangerfield, E Fanning African Journal of Ecology THE INFLUENCE OF ELECTRIC FENCES ON LARGE MAMMAL MOVEMENTS IN THE KILOMBERO VALLEY, TANZANIA C Bonnington, MD Steer, J Lamontagne-Godwin, N Owen, M Grainger African Journal of Ecology EVIDENCE FOR LOCAL DECLINES IN TANZANIA'S PUKU ANTELOPE (KOBUS VARDONI LIVINGSTONE, 1857) POPULATION BETWEEN 2010 1999 AND 2003 African Journal of Ecology

### M Grainger, R Van Aarde, I Whyte

LANDSCAPE HETEROGENEITY AND THE USE OF SPACE BY ELEPHANTS IN THE KRUGER NATIONAL PARK, SOUTH AFRICA

2005